Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994; 7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 4 media boxes, and 8 card catalog drawers; 0.75 Linear Feet in one record carton; 4 videocassettes (hi8); 4 videodiscs (dvd); 192 sound discs (cd); 133 audiocassettes
  - Harris, Helen Frishman, 1993 April 22; 478427 (Box 13, Cassette 60, Box 1, Folder 45, Box 4, Cd 32)
    This interview was conducted on April 22, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Helen Frishman Harris's home in the Dyker Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Harris's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and her family. Harris discusses the death of her mother when she was six months old and her father's second marriage when Harris was four years old. She describes her family's apartments on Broome and Monroe Streets in the LES, the neighborhoods around each apartment, and the family's living arrangements. She discusses her dislike of the public baths, particularly having to bathe with strangers. She discusses attending the Madison House summer camp when she was eight years old and remembers the differences between life in the LES and in the country. She discusses attending events and participating in activities at settlement houses in the LES, in particular the Madison House and an unspecified settlement house on Hester Street. She describes events and customs in the LES surrounding local and national elections. She discusses becoming aware of politics, including joining the American Student Union at Seward Park High School in the LES and attending events in Union Square in Manhattan on May 1. She discusses her family, including her relationship with her stepmother and the fact that her stepmother did not want anyone to know that she was not Harris's mother. Other topics include vermin in the family's apartments, her relationship with her extended family, and ways in which the family members negotiated privacy for themselves in their apartments.
    Duration: 1:13:47
  - Herman, David, 1991 December 7; 478396 (Box 1, Folder 46, Box 12, Cassette 26, Box 3, Cd 37)
    David Herman was born in 1940 in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. His family was Jewish. His father immigrated to the United States (US) from Ukraine, Russia in the 1920s and owned a business decorating dinnerware. His mother immigrated to the US from Poland in the 1920s and worked as a dressmaker. Herman attended a yeshiva through high school. He attended the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan between 1952 and 1958, and studied violin with Louise Behrend. He received his bachelor's degree from New York University in Manhattan and his master's degree from Brooklyn College in Brooklyn. He worked as a high school music teacher, a violin maker, and an artist. He married twice and had three daughters.
    This interview was conducted on December 7, 1991 by Ingrid Melhus at David Herman's home in East Meadow, New York. The interview covers Herman's experiences at the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Herman discusses his parents, their immigration experiences, and their careers. He discusses his education at an unspecified yeshiva in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and describes Williamsburg. He recounts his first experiences in the LES and compares the LES and Williamsburg neighborhoods in the 1950s. He discusses studying the violin at the Music School with Louise Behrend, recalls his memories of his first days at the school, and describes the building in which the school was housed on Pitt Street in the LES. He describes Behrend and her philosophy of teaching violin. He discusses other students at the school, the level at which they were expected to perform, and his participation in the School's orchestra. He discusses his Jewish identity in terms of the time he spent in Williamsburg and in the LES, and the conflict he perceived in expectations of him in the two neighborhoods. He discusses his friends at the School and performances of the orchestra in which he participated. For more interviews about the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement see Baron, Samuel; Behrend, Louise; and Canin, Martin.
    Duration: 46:54
    Henry Street Settlement (New York, N.Y.). Music School
  - Holtzman, Francine, 1994 March 30; 478484 (Box 1, Folder 47, Box 15, Cassette 121A-121B, Box 6, Cd 21-22)
    Francine Holtzman was born in 1918 at Saint Mark's Hospital in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Russia. Holtzman's mother owned a dry goods store in the building in which the family lived at 99 Orchard Street in the LES. Her father ran a pushcart business selling hardware scraps and metals. The family moved several times, but remained in the LES on Orchard and Delancey Streets. Holtzman attended Public School 42 (PS 42) and Seward Park High School in the LES. Holtzman attended the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement. She married and had three children, one of whom died. Her husband managed her mother's business until his death, at which time Holtzman took over, until her retirement 21 years later.
    This interview was conducted on March 30,1994 by Valerie Richmond at Francine Holtzman's house in Queens, New York. The majority of the interview covers Holtzman's memories of the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, including her neighbors and leisure activities, and the death of her son. She describes in detail her neighbor who raised Holtzman while both of her parents worked. She recalls the crowded apartment buildings in the LES and describes her neighbors. She discusses in detail her passion for singing and her lack of interest in school. Holtzman discusses participating in the Loew's Theater Singing Contest in the early 1930s and performing as an adult at Radio City Music Hall in Manhattan and Shea Stadium in Queens. She expresses her sadness over the death of her son, who died when he was 36 years old.
    Duration: 1:33:62
    Parental grief -- New York (State) -- New York.
  - Kahn, Ethel Kokofsky, 1993 May 14; 478428 (Box 1, Folder 48, Box 13, Cassette 61, Box 4, Cd 33)
    Ethel Kokofsky Kahn was born in 1914 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she was one of four children. Both of her parents immigrated to the Unites States in 1907, her father from Poland and her mother from the Galicia region of Poland. Her father worked type casting for the Jewish Daily News in the LES and her mother managed the household. Her parents were members of the Workmen's Circle, Branch 34 in Manhattan. Kahn attended Public Schools 91 and 140 in the LES and Haaren High School in the Midtown area of Manhattan. She worked as a salesperson and was married.
    This interview was conducted on May 14, 1993 by Helen Kugler at Ethel Kokofsky Kahn's home in the Long Island City neighborhood of Queens, New York. The interview covers Kahn's childhood and family. Kahn discusses the different apartments in which her family lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and the ways in which the family members negotiated privacy for themselves in the apartment. She describes their neighbors and her friends from school. She describes her parents, siblings, and extended family who lived with them. She recounts the sewing, washing, and cooking her mother did for the family and describes her father's work casting the metal type for the Jewish Daily News in the LES. She explains that he would bring home the Jewish Daily News and other Yiddish newspapers, which Kahn and her siblings would read to their parents. She discusses her father losing his job when the Jewish Daily News closed and her parents' decision to become janitors in order to save money on rent. See also: Kokofsky, Abraham
    Duration: 1:34:22
  - Kalawsky, Nina Chirko, 1993 May 27; 478429 (Box 13, Cassette 62, Box 1, Folder 49, Box 4, Cd 34)
    Nina Chirko Kalawsky was born in 1938 in New York, New York. Her family was Russian Orthodox and she had two sisters, one of whom died when she was seven years old. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Russia. Her father worked as a watchman for the City of New York and her mother worked as a machine operator in the garment industry. Kalawsky worked as a sales representative.
    This interview was conducted on May 27, 1993 by Doris Charrow at Nina Chirko Kalawsky's home in New Hyde Park, New York. The interview covers Kalawsky's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and her family. Throughout the interview, Kalawsky describes her family's apartments in the LES, living arrangements in the apartments, appliances in the apartments, the ways in which the family members negotiated privacy for themselves in the apartment. She discusses her parents' responsibilities as the janitors in the buildings in which they lived. She discusses her mother, her jobs outside of the home, and her feelings about working outside of the home, in particular her enjoyment of discussing politics with her coworkers. She discusses her father's work for the City of New York as a watchman on construction sites. She discusses her parents' relationship and their immigration experiences. She discusses her Irish neighbors, a Catholic church in her neighborhood to which she wanted to belong, and the fact that she wanted to be Irish rather than Russian. Kalawsky discusses the death of her oldest sister from spinal meningitis when she was seven years old and her mother's feelings about illness in the family after the death of her daughter. She discusses her relationship with her parents, the fact that her mother worried over her safety and the games and skills her father taught her. She recalls her memories of the different ethnic groups that lived together in the LES, in particular the foods of each group and her opinion that the diversity was beneficial to the people living in the neighborhood. Other topics include traditions in her home during Easter and Christmas and games she would play with her friends.
    Duration: 1:30:32
  - Kaplan, Louis, 1992 October 26; 478560 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Louis Kaplan was born in the early 20th century in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish and he was an only child. His parents immigrated to the United States from Russia in 1902. His father worked as a tailor and in a saloon before leaving his family to become a bootlegger in Boston, Massachusetts. His mother worked in Macy's in Manhattan and died in 1942. Kaplan attended Public School 25 in Manhattan and worked as a diamond setter. He married and did not have children.
    This interview was conducted on October 26, 1992 by Helen Selsdon at the Educational Alliance in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The audio recording of the interview is missing. The interview covers Louis Kaplan's family. Kaplan describes his parents, their careers, and his relationship with each of them. He discusses his mother's illness and death in 1942.
  - Katz, Michael, 1991 October 16; 478397 (Box 12, Cassette 27, Box 3, Cd 38)
    Michael Katz was born in 1912. His family was Jewish and had five brothers and one sister. His parents immigrated to the United States from Poland, via England, and settled in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His father worked as machine operator in a garment factory and a dishwasher. Katz attended Seward Park High School in the LES. He was a founding member of the Henry Street Oldtimers at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES and served as the president of the Henry Street Settlement Federal Credit Union. He married and had children. He worked as a salesman.
    This interview was conducted on October 16, 1991 by an unidentified interviewer at an unspecified location. The interview covers Michael Katz's life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and his involvement in the Henry Street Oldtimers at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES. At the beginning and end of the interview, Katz discusses the work of the Henry Street Oldtimers at the Henry Street Settlement and members of the Oldtimers. He discusses the reasons for the creation of the Oldtimers in 1938 and the importance of the Henry Street Settlement to him, his friends, and his brothers as children. He discusses his role as president of the Henry Street Settlement Federal Credit Union and recounts the creation of the credit union. He discusses his childhood in the LES, his reasons for joining the Henry Street Settlement, and activities in which he participated there. He discusses his father's working life, the family's living arrangements in small apartments in the LES, and his parents' immigration experiences. He discusses his education, his dislike of school, and his preference for meeting friends in pool halls rather than attending school. He recounts his family's reaction to his brother's marriage to a Catholic and the fact that his mother would not speak to him for two years after his marriage. He discusses organizations in which he was involved at the time of the interview and his volunteer work through the Henry Street Settlement and an unspecified Masonic lodge. Other topics include his siblings and his work as a salesman.
    Duration: 1:31:26
  - Katz, Selma Herschowitz, 1992 October 20; 478380 (Box 1, Folder 51, Box 11, Cassette 6A-6B, Box 3, Cd 11-12)
    Selma Herschowitz Katz was born in 1913 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and was one of five children. Her parents immigrated to the United States in the 1910s, her father from Romania and her mother from Austria. Her father had a number of jobs before opening a men's clothing store in the LES and her mother worked as a nurse and as an operator in a factory. Katz worked as a salesperson in department stores and attended programs at the Henry Street Settlement. She married and had seven children. In addition to the LES, she lived in the Bronx, Brooklyn, and Queens.
    This interview was conducted on October 20, 1992 by Aimee Kaplan at Selma Herschowitz Katz's apartment in Queens, New York. The interview covers Katz's childhood, her family, and her working life. Katz discusses her parents, including her father's many jobs, her parents' divorce, and her father's relationship with Katz and her siblings after the divorce. She discusses her marriage, including childbirth and her decision to use birth control. She discusses living with her mother and other family members after her marriage and the ways in which people negotiated privacy for themselves while living in close proximity with many family members. Katz recounts social activities in which she participated as a child and young woman, and with her husband after their children were older. Other topics include her children, her husband's jobs, her involvement in the Flushing chapter of Hadassah, and her religious views.
    Duration: 2:03:15
  - Kertman, Moe, 1994 March 8; 478485 (Box 16, Cassette 120, Box 1, Folder 52, Box 6, Cd 23)
    Moe Kertman was born into a Jewish family in Poland. In Poland, his father worked. His family immigrated to the United States (US) when Kertman was a child and settled in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His father worked in a paper bag factory in Poland and later owned a wholesale business in the US. His mother worked as a seamstress. When he was 10 years old, Kertman was a member of the Communist Party of the United States of America. He worked as a peddler and at a wholesale pharmacy in the LES.
    This interview was conducted on an unspecified date by an unspecified interviewer at an unspecified location. The majority of the interview covers Moe Kertman's efforts to avoid becoming Americanized and his membership in the Russian Social Democratic Party. He recalls his struggle to conform to American culture and the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Kertman describes the LES as very crowded and explains that he thought the majority of the residents had become Americanized and that he felt excluded because of this. Kertman discusses his feelings about this Americanization and he disapproval for the immigrants who, in his opinion, had abandoned their home country's language, attitude and general way of life. He explains that he found purpose and community within the Communist Party of the United States of America because they were activity in the community and stood for causes that he felt would better society.
    Duration: 47:07
  - Kiriakos, Philip, 1991 October 11; 478398 (Box 12, Cassette 28, Box 1, Folder 53, Box 3, Cd 39)
    Philip Kiriakos was born in 1913 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Roman Catholic and he was one of eight children. His father worked as a bartender until 1929 when he opened a garage. He worked in his father's garage until it closed in 1936, as a truck driver between 1936 and 1946, and as a cargo checker for the Cunard Line on the docks in New York between 1946 and 1976, when he retired. He was married and had two daughters. In 1939, he and his family moved into the Vladeck Houses in the LES.
    This interview was conducted on October 11, 1991 by Ulrike Daehnhardt at the Henry Street Settlement's Home Planning Workshop at the Vladeck Houses in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Philip Kiriakos's childhood, family, and experiences as a tenant of the Vladeck Houses. He describes his daughters and discusses the deaths of his elder daughter in 1983 and his wife in 1988. He recounts learning about the Vladeck Houses and being one of the first families to move into the apartments. He discusses the differences between life in the tenements and Vladeck Houses, including having bathrooms inside the apartment and having rent determined by the occupants' salaries. He discusses crime in the Vladeck Houses and other housing projects at the time of the interview and his opinion that the Vladeck Houses are better than other housing projects. He discusses his neighbors and his decision to stay in the Vladeck Houses because of his relationship with one family. He recounts life in the tenements in the 1910s and 1920s, including Christmas and New Year's traditions, trolleys in front of the buildings, and ways to keep cool in the summer. Other topics include his participation in a theatre group at the Church of St. James in Manhattan and different jobs he held.
    Duration: 1:25:44
  - Koblenz, Beatrice Schlanger, 1993 September 6; 478430 (Box 1, Folder 54, Box 13, Cassette 63, Box 4, Cd 35)
    Beatrice Schlanger Koblenz was born in 1921 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Lezajsk in the Polish region of Russia and worked in a factory. Her mother immigrated to the US from Austria and managed the household. Koblenz lost her hearing when she was nine years old. She attended Washington Irving High School in Manhattan. She was an artist and worked in the civil service in the City of New York for 31 years. She was married and had two children.
    This interview was conducted on September 6, 1993 by Helen Goodman in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Beatrice Schlanger Koblenz's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and her family. Koblenz assisted throughout the interview by an interpreter from the League for the Hard of Hearing in Manhattan and is sometimes hard to understand. Koblenz describes her family's apartment on Eldridge Street in the LES, the living arrangements, and her neighbors in her building. She discusses traditions in her family surrounding Passover and her father's responsibilities as the sexton in their synagogue. Other topics include vermin in the family's apartment, her mother's home remedies, fires in the LES, and games Koblenz would play with her friends on the street.
    Duration: 50:27
  - Kokofsky, Abraham, 1993 June 8; 478431 (Box 13, Cassette 64, Box 1, Folder 55, Box 4, Cd 36)
    Abraham Kokofsky was born in New York, New York in 1911. His family was Jewish and he had three siblings. His father immigrated to the United States (US) from Russia and worked as a laborer at the Jewish Daily News, or Yiddisher Tageblatt. His mother immigrated to the US from Poland and managed the household. The family lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Kokofsky attended Seward Park High School in the LES. Kokofsky worked for the United States Postal Service and was a member of the American Postal Workers Union.
    This interview was conducted on June 8, 1993 by Goldie Gold in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Abraham Kokofsky's early life and family. Kokofsky describes the apartments in which his family lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan and the living arrangements in them. He describes his father's work as a laborer at the Jewish Daily News, or Yiddisher Tageblatt. He discusses a kheyder he attended near Suffolk and Attorney Streets, the corporal punishment inflicted on the students, and his refusal to return after receiving a beating. He discusses his and his siblings' education and their leaving school in order to work to support the family. He discusses his childhood friends and his feelings about non-Jewish people as a young person. He discusses his participation in a choir in an unspecified synagogue, despite the fact that his family were not strictly observant. He describes his parents and discusses his relationship with them, in particular his negative feelings about his mother and his preference for his father. He discusses his membership in the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union when he worked in the garment industry and his membership in the American Postal Workers Union when he worked for the United States Postal Service. Other topics include the family's experiences during the Great Depression, his siblings' working lives, and his friendships with Zero Mostel and his brother that developed in the synagogue choir.
    Duration: 1:31:09
  - Landres, Joel, 1991 October 31; 478399 (Box 12, Cassette 29, Box 3, Cd 40)
    Joel Landres was born into a Jewish family in a small village near Minsk, Russia in 1904. In October 1913, his family immigrated to the United States and lived for a brief time on Cherry Street in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Over the next five years, the family moved to five different apartments within the LEs. When he was nine years old, Landres and 14 of his classmates formed a club called the Wilson Club. Landres was an active member of the Henry Street Settlement in Manhattan and worked at Camp Henry.